Finding Aid for Michigan Audubon Society Records 1913-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Audubon Society Records 1913-1992, 1913-1988
Michigan Audubon Society.
4.75 linear feet
State Audubon society established in 1904; records include historical and background information; files of annual meetings of executive committee and board of directors; files relating society's activities, to its nature centers and bird sanctuaries, and to the operation and activities of local chapters within the state; also correspondence and scattered photographs.
0064 Bn 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were donated by the Michigan Audubon Society in 1999. (Donor no. 8868 )
The collection is open for research.
The Michigan Audubon Society was formed in 1904. Michigan was the thirty-fourth state to organize an Audubon society. The Michigan society, like all Audubon societies, evolved out of the "protection committee" of the American Ornithologists' Union. In 1904 William Dutcher, the chairman of the committee, wrote that the Audubon movement was the outgrowth of well known ornithologist J.J. Audubon's "love of nature and his desire to preserve birds." In 1904 the society listed its purposes as the following: "To disseminate information respecting the economic value of birds to agriculture, and their importance to the welfare of man; to discourage the purpose or use of feathers of birds for ornamentation, except those of the ostrich and domesticated fowl; to discourage the destruction of wild birds and their eggs, except for scientific purposes; to establish Bird day exercises in the schools of the State of Michigan, in connection with the celebration of Arbor Day and to encourage the introduction of bird study in schools." At the time the club was formed birds were being "destroyed and exploited." Officers of the society often gave lectures, and distributed pamphlets, bulletins and leaflets, throughout the state in order to educate the public about the destruction of birds.
Since its formation the society has continued its bird protection efforts and has greatly expanded the scope of its activities. In 1923 a society newsletter was started. This newsletter later grew into a quarterly journal called Jack Pine Warbler. In 1929 the society organized a statewide poll of school children in order to select a state bird. The society also established Junior Recruit and Junior Audubon programs, and began holding summer nature camps for children. The society also began to lobby for legislation which would assist in their bird protection efforts. Local chapters of the society began to form, to assist in the efforts of the state organization.
Over time the society became involved in more general conservation efforts. In addition to the preservation and protection of birds, it became a goal of the society to "conserve the wildlife and the natural beauty in Michigan in all practical ways and to cooperate with other organizations which are working for true conservation of natural resources." The society acquired the Bernard Baker Sanctuary in Calhoun County, the Seven Ponds Nature Sanctuary in Lapeer County, and the Sarrett Nature Sanctuary in St. Joseph Valley, and worked to promote legislation which would protect birds, and the environment as a whole. Today the Michigan Audubon Society has over 10,000 members, and continues its varied conservation efforts.
The Michigan Audubon Society records document the development and management of the organization, its conservation activities, including development of nature centers and sanctuaries, and the society's relations with local chapters. The record group is divided into the following series: History and Background; Meetings and Meeting Minutes; Activities; Nature Centers and Sanctuaries; Local Chapters; Correspondence; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Audubon societies--Michigan.; Birds--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Bird refuges--Michigan.; Nature centers--Michigan.; Michigan Audubon Society.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Birds--Michigan.; Children--Michigan.; Michigan Audubon Society.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- History and Background
  The History and Background series is comprised of material documenting the history of the society. It includes written histories of the organization as well material such as membership handbooks, and the society's constitution and bylaws.
  - History 1904-1934 (Box 1)
  - History 1904-1954 (Box 1)
  - General descriptions of the organization undated (Box 1)
  - Constitutions and Bylaws 1956, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Member handbooks 1959, 1972 (Box 1)
- Meetings and Meeting Minutes
  The Meetings and Meeting Minutes series documents the annual meetings of the society, as well as the meetings of the organization's executive committee and board of directors. Annual meeting material includes copies of programs distributed to attendees, as well as annual reports of the president or board of directors. These reports usually include financial information, as well as a general summary of the clubs activities. The annual meetings subseries also include annual reports from the various committees involved in the origination. These committees vary over the years but may include the Finance Committee, the Bookshop Committee, the Chapter Relations Committee, the Conservation Committee, the Endowment Committee, the Education Committee, the Field Activities Committee, the Public Relations Committee, the Research and Publications Committee, and the Sanctuary Committee. The annual meeting subseries also contains correspondence relating to the meetings.
  - Annual meetings
    - 1913-1973, 44 folders (Box 1)
      (lacking 1927, 1930-1933, 1935-1938, 1940
  - Executive Committee meeting minutes
    The Executive Committee meeting minutes subseries contains material documenting the, goals and strategies of the society. These meeting minutes also usually include a treasurer's report.
    - 1923-1930, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - 1941-1944 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1970, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - 1971-1978, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors meeting minutes
    The Board of Director's meeting minutes also document the organization's goals and strategies. However, this subseries contains more specific information about the activities of the club. In later years (after 1957) these meetings usually contain reports from the organizations various committees.
    - 1945-1978, 23 folders (Box 2)
- Activities
  The Activities series is comprised of material relating to the organization's varied activities. It includes records of the research on the birds of Michigan that has been conducted by the society. This research includes various attempts to count the different species of birds in Michigan, as well as projects focusing on specific types of birds. There is a particularly strong subseries on the Jack Pine or Kirtland Warbler. Also included in the Activity Series is documentation of the Society's efforts to promote and lobby for environmental legislation. The series also contains the records of the Jr. Audubon Society and summer camps run by the society, as well as publicity material produced by the society and material documenting the production of the society's newsletters and other publications. It also includes records documenting the society's efforts to track down the descendants of J.J. Audubon, and its efforts to memorialize Audubon himself. The activities series also includes a subseries of miscellaneous activities, including a contest held by the club to name the state bird of Michigan, various lectures sponsored by the club, related newspaper clippings.
  - Jr. Audubon Society
    - Formation and administration 1948-1957 (Box 2)
    - Educational Materials 1947-1957 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Camps
    - Nature Councilors Training Camp 1953, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Junior Councilors Baker Day Camp 1950-1970 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Camps 1954-1966 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Publicity and publications
    - Jack Pine Warbler, administrative records and correspondence 1978-1985 (Box 2)
    - Enjoying Birds in Michigan, administrative records and correspondence 1973, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Birding Hot Spots in Michigan, administrative records and correspondence 1986 (Box 3)
    - Sanctuary Notes 1971 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous publicity pamphlets and information (Box 3)
  - J.J. Audubon
    - Memorials 1929-1933 (Box 3)
    - Searching for descendants 1924 (Box 3)
  - Legislation efforts
    - Non-Game fund legislation 1983-1986 (Box 3)
    - Off-Road vehicle legislation 1974-1978 (Box 3)
    - Falconry Bill (S.B. 717) 1978 (Box 3)
  - Research
    - Committee reports and correspondence 1979-1987 (scattered dates) (Box 3)
    - Gull/Shorebird banding 1976 (Box 3)
    - Nest record program 1976-1978 (Box 3)
    - Spring Bird Count 1981-1985 (Scattered dates) (Box 3)
    - Christmas Bird Count 1986 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Winter Bird Feeder Count 1971-1988 (scattered dates) (Box 3)
    - Michigan Breeding Bird Atlas 1983-1987 (Box 3)
    - Birding Area Guides and Information 1967-1977 (scattered dates) (Box 3)
    - Rare Bird Alerts 1982 (Box 3)
    - Kirtland/Jack Pine Warbler 1971-1986 (scattered dates), 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous activities
    - State Bird Naming Contest 1929 (Box 3)
    - Lectures (scattered dates) (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1920-1950 (scattered dates) (Box 3)
    - General Conservation Reports, scattered dates (Box 3)
    - Bookshop 1961 (Box 3)
    - Edith Munger Memorial Fund 1934 (Box 3)
    - Local Chapters 1940-1966 (scattered dates) (Box 3)
- Nature Centers and Sanctuaries
  The Nature Centers and Sanctuaries series contains the records of the Sarrett Nature Center as well as the Seven Ponds Nature Sanctuary. Included are bylaws and legal documents, committee meeting minutes, committee and director reports, general and publicity information, grant information, newspaper clippings, and correspondence.
  - Sarrett Nature Sanctuary
    - Correspondence, Reports, and Meeting Minutes 1964-1990, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Seven Ponds Nature Center
    - General Information and Publicity 1967-1972 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
    - By-laws and Legal documents 1977, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Grants 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings 1972, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Board Meeting Minutes 1966-1990, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Local Chapters
  The Local Chapters series contains material related to the local chapters of the Michigan Audubon Society. The series contains meeting minutes of the state society Chapter Relations Committee as well as newspaper clippings sent to the State society form the local chapters. The bulk of the series consists of an alphabetical listing of current and former local chapters. This material consists mainly of correspondence between local chapters and the state organization. Documentation of the activities of the local chapters is often included within the correspondence. The series also includes information about the officers of the local chapters, and sometimes contains newsletters of the chapters.
  - Chapter Relations Committee, general information and correspondence 1959-1983 (Box 4)
  - Local Chapter Workshop 1985 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings from Local Chapters (Box 4)
  - Local Chapter Correspondence and general information
    - Baker Area Audubon Chapter 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - Bay City Audubon Club 1940-1967, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Bay de Noc Audubon Club 1974-1982 (Box 4)
    - Benzie Audubon Society 1975-1980 (Box 4)
    - Berrien Springs Audubon Society 1973, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Blue Water Audubon Society 1970-1985 (Box 4)
    - Capital Area (Lansing) Audubon Society 1971-1989 (Box 4)
    - Cass County Audubon Society 1977-1979 (Box 4)
    - Chappee Rapids Audubon Club 1983 (Box 4)
    - Cheboygan Audubon Club 1983 (Box 4)
    - Copper County Audubon Club 1976, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Chippewa Valley Audubon Club 1972-1986 (Box 4)
    - Detroit Audubon Club 1944-1945 (Box 4)
    - Grand Rapids Audubon Club 1970-1988 (Box 4)
    - Gross Point Chapter 1966-1972 (Box 4)
    - Genesee County Audubon Society 1957-1979 (Box 4)
    - Hartland Nature Club 1965-1977 (Box 4)
    - Holland Audubon Club 1982-1989 (Box 4)
    - Hillsdale County Audubon Society 1954, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Huron Audubon Club 1987-1990 (Box 4)
    - Iosco Audubon Society 1973-1986 (Box 4)
    - Jackson Audubon Society 1957-1992, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Kalamazoo Audubon Society 1964-1987, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Lapeer County Audubon Society 1959-1979 (Box 4)
    - Macomb Audubon Society 1975-1992 (Box 4)
    - Manistee Audubon Society 1989-1991 (Box 4)
    - Marquette County Audubon Society 1958-1973 (Box 4)
    - Mecosta Audubon Club 1973-1982 (Box 4)
    - Michiana Audubon Club 1970-1976 (Box 4)
    - Midland Audubon Club 1966-1989 (Box 5)
    - Muskegon County Audubon Club 1977-1985 (Box 5)
    - Newaygo County Audubon Club 1990-1992 (Box 5)
    - Northland Audubon Society 1982-1989 (Box 5)
    - Oakland (formerly Pontiac) County Audubon Club 1958-1992 (Box 5)
    - Oceana Audubon Society 1982-1998 (Box 5)
    - Olivet Nature Trails Club 1959-1978 (Box 5)
    - Oronko Bird Club 1965 (Box 5)
    - Petoskey Regional Audubon Society 1971-1987 (Box 5)
    - Pigeon River Audubon club 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    - Porcupine Mountain Audubon Club 1986-1988 (Box 5)
    - Pine River Audubon Club 1976, 1982 (Box 5)
    - Saginaw Valley Audubon Club 1958-1986 (Box 5)
    - Sault Naturalists Club 1968-1982, 1991, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Thunder Bay Audubon Club 1965-1971 (Box 5)
    - Tobico Audubon Club 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Traverse City (Walter Hastings) Audubon Club 1958-1984, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Washtenaw Audubon Society 1966-1984 (Box 5)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series includes general correspondence to and from members of the society, as well as letters to Congressmen asking for support in various conservation efforts. Also included is the correspondence of Dr. L.H. Walkinshaw, a vice president of the society who was active in the society's efforts to acquire the Baker Sanctuary in Calhoun County.
  - General Correspondence 1920-1950 (Box 5)
  - General Correspondence 1963-1964 (Box 5)
  - With Dr. L.H. Walkinshaw about Baker Sanctuary 1939-1949 (Box 5)
- Photographs
  The Photograph series contains small pictures of owls and other birds and bird eggs. Also included are several pictures of the Jack Pine Warbler. The series also contains photographs from the Junior Audubon Society camps and activities, and three pictures of the Seven Ponds Nature Center.
  - Junior Audubon Society undated (Box 5)
    (includes children examining various animals, children using a chemistry set, children presenting nature projects)
  - Kirtland/Jack Pine Warbler undated (Box 5)
    (includes three photos of the Kirtland Warbler and one photo of the presentation of a painting of the bird)
  - Seven Ponds Nature Center, includes three photos of landscape and flowers 1970, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous birds undated (Box 5)
    (includes several small pictures of owls and other birds and bird eggs)